<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An aduertisement to the King of Nauarre, to vnite him selfe with the King and the Catholique faithe Beeing in trueth a very slaunderous, false, and seditious libell, against the said King of Nauarre, and other Christian princes ... Truely translated according to the copy printed in French.</title>
            <title>Advertissement au roy de Navarre de se reunir avec le roy &amp; la foy catholique. English.</title>
            <author>Maillard, André, fl. 1585-1591.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1585</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 53 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 22 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A02984</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 13127</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S120341</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99855540</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99855540</idno>
            <idno type="VID">21035</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A02984)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 21035)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 639:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An aduertisement to the King of Nauarre, to vnite him selfe with the King and the Catholique faithe Beeing in trueth a very slaunderous, false, and seditious libell, against the said King of Nauarre, and other Christian princes ... Truely translated according to the copy printed in French.</title>
                  <title>Advertissement au roy de Navarre de se reunir avec le roy &amp; la foy catholique. English.</title>
                  <author>Maillard, André, fl. 1585-1591.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 37, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1585]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A translation of: Maillard, André.  Advertissement au roy de Navarre de se reunir avec le roy &amp; la foy catholique.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>France. --  Sovereign (1589-1610 : Henry IV). --  Declaration of the king of Navarre, touching the slaunders published against him by those of the league --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:21035:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:21035:1"/>
            <p>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>An Aduertiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to the <hi>KJNG</hi> of <hi>NA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ARRE, to vnite him ſelfe</hi> with the KING and the Catholique Faithe.</p>
            <p>Beeing in trueth a very ſlaunderous, falſe, and ſeditious Libell, againſt the ſaid KING o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> NAVARRE, and other Chriſtian Princes made as an anſwere to his Book intituled: <hi>Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Declaration of the</hi> KING <hi>of</hi> NAVARRE, <hi>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> touching the ſlaunders publiſhed againſt him</hi> &amp;c which is heer extant in Engliſh. But this beeing ſubtilly conuayed, vnder pretence of winning him to the Romiſh Religion, is therefore the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſet downe in the ſame nature as it is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten: to ſhowe a wicked minde againſt GOD, the King, and the ſinceritie of true Religion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Truely tranſlated according to the Copy Printed in French.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:21035:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:21035:2"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Efore thou enter into this diſcourſe (Gentle Reader) I am to admoniſh thee of certaine ſpeciall poyntes, whereof I would deſire thee to haue ſome regarde. Firſt as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning this Pamphlet, it is made as an anſwere to a very modeſt and dutifull declaration, written by the KING of
<pb facs="tcp:21035:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
NAVARRE, to the King his ſoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne Lord, as concerning the ſlaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders publiſhed againſt him &amp;c.</p>
            <p>And heerin, by many needleſſe ſhifts and palpable cauilles, he laboreth to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueigh againſt the ſaide King, becauſe of his Chriſtian Religion, and for that he wil not ſtoup to the man of Roome. In al which windlaſſes, he dooth but waſte time, with high woordes and termes of diſgrace, againſt thoſe who with all hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militie, are content to beare the heauie yoke for their maiſters ſake, which the aduerſſenes of the time laieth vppon them, and God hath appointed to make triall of his Children.</p>
            <p>Secondly, for the contempt he ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth of Religion, and aduauncing of the inuentions and traditions of men, flatly condemning the Chriſtians, who leane only to the woord of God, contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the olde and new Teſtament, and
<pb facs="tcp:21035:3"/>
who will beleeue no other doctrine, though an Angell ſhould reueale it from Heauen: I doubt not but his childiſh, groſſe and abſurd reaſons, will be very eaſely perceiued, and ſpecially of the lear<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned, who knowe that better wine neuer comes from ſuch veſſels, nor greater rea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſons from ſuch ſenceleſſe cauillers, ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore rather to be pitied for their folly, then enuied, becauſe we will ſhewe more Chriſtian charitie.</p>
            <p>Laſtly where he inuaieth againſt our Cuntry of ENGLAND, and entreth into matters aboue my reach: I muſt leaue them to the Iudgement of ſuch, who are better acquainted with ſuch high poyntes, albeit I beleeue them to be meere falſe, and vttered vpon a mallici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſtomack. What els is in this lewd <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd ſlaunderous Pamphelet, of bad na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ure (as it is all) or hurtfull to any, as I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ould be loth, I leaue it to the good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration
<pb facs="tcp:21035:4"/>
of ſuch, who dayly beholde the mallice of Sathan and his miniſters, againſt the godly and well inclined, and therfore to ioyne with me in praier, that God wil either ſoone amend them, or end them.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:21035:4"/>
            <head>¶ An Aduertiſement to the <hi>KJNG of NA<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ARRE,</hi> to vnite him ſelfe with the <hi>KING</hi> and the <hi>Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique</hi> Faythe.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>IR,</hi> I doo not think that it were ſufficient for you, to flat<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter your own humour with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſucceſſion of a young Prince, healthfull, and welbeloued of his Subiects, as our King is, except (conſidering the ſtate wherin you now ſtand) it were expedient and auailable for you, to followe the councell which many take occaſion to giue you, vpon the chaunce which now of late hath drawne you néerer to this Crowne. But becauſe that God often ſendes vs many likelyhoods of ſome proſperitie néere at hand, not to the end that we ſhould aſſure our ſelues of the end ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of: But the rather, that vpon the doubt of the euent, we may change the preſent condition of our life. Therupon I hope, that the King our Lord wil not miſlike, if I ſet before your eyes, how néere you are to his ſucceſſion, to preuaile therwith ſo farre as it will extend towards you, in the eſtate wherin you are:
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:21035:5"/>
and not as a thing to be hoped for of you, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to be wiſhed for by any other.</p>
            <p>Now it is credible enough, that (you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſuch a great Prince) in a Realme, where the people are ſéen to be deuided by the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarietie in religion and beléef (as God hath ſuffered this to be) your Maieſtie hath on both ſides many ſeruants, who are all deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous of your proſperity, and doo imbrace by a common vowe, the eſtabliſhment of your good fortune. But in reſpect of things preſent, and thoſe which may be iudged to happen héerafter: it is not hard in deliberation to to knowe, which of them beareth moſte good will to your ſeruice. Thoſe (Sir) who moſte of all haue reſpect to the welfare, and benefit of their Cuntrie, and euermore haue cléeued to the fourmes, ancient inſtitutions, and faithful obedience to their Maiſter, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be in any wiſe ſuſpected, to wiſh malici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly any mutation or chaunge in this e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate, wherin, all things are to them peacea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and happy: for ſo much as they knowe them ſelues to be in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fauour and good grace of their Prince, reſpected, and bearing the good will of the people, and eſtéemed of them who (vnder the Kings authoritie) haue the gouernment of the Lawes, and pollicy of the Realme.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:21035:5"/>Furthermore, no more hope to be repo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in you, then in any other, cannot make them deſirous to ſée you weare this crowne: for if you had vpon the chaunce of a Dye loſt your parte, their good behauiour paſt, and the remembrance of their fidelitie, will no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing deminiſh their hopes (whoſoeuer ſhal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be lawfull King) to finde all fauour and good countenance. But if amongſt thoſe that haue taken in hand to giue you councell, there be ſome, (which for the bringing in of nouel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, wherby they haue made the eſtate their enemie) haue not their owne eſtate in good aſſurance, it is your part (Sir) to Iudge, which of them you eſtéeme to giue you the ſoundeſt councel: either of ſuch as in danger of ſhipwrack holde you faſt, as it were to the Maſt, or ſome other ſure holde, yet delu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding you with imagined hopes, but benefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall to their intereſt: or of ſuch who hauing no occaſion of feare, doo expect of your good Fortune no better condition, then that they enioy at this preſent, and make account of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he ſame héerafter, whoſoeuer ſhall lawful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y ſuccéed in this eſtate.</p>
            <p>As for the one, we néed no better proofe to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>howe you, that they giue you no other coun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>el, but that which they think beneficiall for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hem ſelues, and not for you. If you
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:21035:6"/>
would conſider and mark what they tel you, that your return to the Catholique Religion ſhould be but in vaine, becauſe it wil neither be acceptable to the King or profitable to the Catholiques: therby they ſufficiently diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer the conſequence which they wil inferre, which is, that you ought not to haue any other conſideratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of what Religion you be, ſauing for the profit which you may bring vnto them that doo likewiſe imbrace the ſame.</p>
            <p>This I will graunt them alwaies, that neither the King nor the Catholiques his good Subiects, are drawen by any other reſpect to call you againe into the Church, wherin you receiued y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> firſt mark of a chriſti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>an: but only by the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon compaſſion, which euery honeſt and good natured man feeleth to haue in him ſelf, on ſuch, as either through errour in iudgement, or by ſeducement and impoſture of others, doo forſake firſt the right way to their ſaluation, and afterwarde doo depriue them ſelues of all the good and hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py ſucceſſe, which might happen to them du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring this life. Although the rigorous puniſh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ments, which the Lawes of all Nations haue ordained againſt the <hi>Miſcreants,</hi> dooth render vs a cléere and ſufficient teſtimony, how naturall it is for men to abhorre, ſuch as they iudge to holde any peruerſe opinion,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:21035:6"/>
in that which concernes the beléef and the ſeruice of God. So that if it be true, that each one hath grounded and eſtabliſhed in him ſelfe the ſame opinion, which they ſuppoſe and iudge to be in al other: it is to be thought and verily beléeued, that he which eſtéemeth that ſo few people doo little care, that others ſhould be different in Religion to them, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept they haue ſome particuler intereſt ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>in, that man may be ſaid to be very little re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious.</p>
            <p>And to ſpeak to you fréely of the deſire which the King may haue, that you were be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come Catholique: it cannot be attributed to any co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>modity wherof he ſhould liue in hope, neither that he ſhould think, that your fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour and frendſhip might be to him of any importance. God hath giuen him ſo great au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie ouer you and your hability: y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> what<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſoeuer you were, he knoweth very wel, that ſince you be borne his ſubiect, you neither ought nor can doo otherwiſe, but y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> you ſhould be obedient to his wil and commaundement. As concerning if he doo not loue you: it is for you to ſéek by humble ſeruice, that he would admit you againe into his good grace and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour.</p>
            <p>You are too well brought vp Sir, and you haue too much intereſt to knowe, what is the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:21035:7"/>
greatnes and authority of a King of <hi>Fraunce,</hi> to beléeue, that he may deſire, that one of his owne Subiects ſhould be of one ſelf ſame, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion, rather then of an other, therby to make him his better fréend. If he had no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther conſideration then this only, in trueth he hath no néed greatly to care whether you were an <hi>Huguenot</hi> or a Catholique: and if he ſhould ſée any inco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uenience therin, he ſhould be but a beholder of the imminent danger to fall vpon your own head. But in reſpect y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he is a Prince, who euen by nature is good and gratious, it is not to be doubted, but that he could wiſh that as well you, as all other his Subiects, were brought into ſuch an order and condition of life, wherin he might truſt that God ſhould finde your actions more con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>firmable, but yours moſte eſpecially. Sir, you ought to perſwade and aſſure your ſelfe, more then any other may, of his good and kinde affection towards you, in that you are (as things are now come to paſſe) the very néereſt ſucceſſour vnto his Crowne, and in that (beſides this) you haue his only Siſter to your eſpouſe and wife.</p>
            <p>To ſet before your eyes, that he would take this your ſuddaine change in Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, for a demonſtration of the deſire which you haue, that he might yéeld you his place
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:21035:7"/>
quickly: that is as much as to ſpeak of a thing, wherin there is no likelyhood at all. For if he might be perſwaded, that ſuch a vile or wicked intent could inter into your hart: you muſt holde if for a certainty, that he would beleue, it would ſooner créep into your minde being a <hi>Huguenot,</hi> then a Catholique.</p>
            <p>Furthermore, who euer heard ſay, that one to make him ſelf woorthy to ſuccéed into an eſtate, ſhould for that cauſe deſire y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> death of him that is in poſſeſſion therof? It would followe by conſequence, that in all the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grées of Fortune, the moſte néereſt kinſmen ſhould be the moſte mortal and deadly ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies one to another: and that the Parents ſhould neuer regarde their Children more reſpectiuely, then whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (by their behauiours) they cauſe them to perceiue, that they are indifferent whether they be their inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours or no. Contrariwiſe, the King wil at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute this your conuerſion to a particuler and wonderfull grace of God ſhowed vnto you, by reducing you againe into the lappe of the Church, and into the way of our ſalua<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion, by a more méeke, gentle and humaine meanes, then thoſe which men haue vſed héertofore to bring you to the ſame.</p>
            <p>As touching the other Catholique Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects of the King, I reſt in this minde, that
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:21035:8"/>
they deſire not your returne to the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Religion of your Aunceſters, for any ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uantage they hope to haue therby: wherby you may Iudge, that they are better affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned vnto you then thoſe, who for their grée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy hope of Couetouſnes, goe about to keep you in their pretended Religion. And this ſhould be (Sir) properly to deceiue you, that you ſhould perſwade your ſelfe, that the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholiques are mooued by ſome kinde of feare leaſt the Crowne ſhould falle vpon the head of ſome <hi>Huguenot.</hi> That man may be thought very weake in iudgement, and that his ſences are very much troubled, who dooth not perfectly perſwade himſelf: that no other (in this our age) but a Catholique ſhall be admitted vnto the Crowne of <hi>Fraunce,</hi> and we doo not think that any man did euer ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine the contrary.</p>
            <p>As touching the reſt, they haue good rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to perſwade you, that the catholiques do not wiſh you to be on their ſide, that by this mean it might be eaſier for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to extinguiſh the <hi>Huguenots</hi> Religion: for we are ſo fully ſatiſfied of that, which hetherto we haue doon vnto them vnder the commaundement of the King: that hence forward we iudge them not to haue any hability of continuaunce, except it be only through our méeknes and
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:21035:8"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>I cannot very well conceiue what theſe Catholiques ſhould be, which your diſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers and aduiſers doo call pollitique: but this I knowe, that we are al indifferently affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned for the defence of our Religion, the conſeruation of our Lawes, and the reſt and quietnes of our Country. But if they giue that name to thoſe which are amongſt vs, and which haue ſome particuler bond and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uotion to doo you ſeruice, as it is not to be doubted, but that there are many in this Realme: Yet for all that they are greatly de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceiued, if they hope that theſe haue in ſmal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler eſtimation the ancient fourmes of the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate, the quietnes of their conſciences, and commodities of their liues, then the other haue. I am perſwaded Sir, that if you ſhould appeale vpon your owne particuler intereſt, they would aduenture their liues very wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly, to doo you ſeruice: but in this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that concerneth Religion, which is ſuch a zeale and affection, as nature hath imprin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the harts of al men, it paſſeth all bo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds and duties which one man hath gotten ouer an other.</p>
            <p>But that which we eſtéeme more neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary to doo, is, to pray to God, that it would ſo pleaſe him to inſpire you, that you might
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:21035:9"/>
rather followe thoſe meanes, wherby <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the generall plauditie and reioycing of the people) you may be receiued and honored: ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then that by ſwoord and fire, you ſhould offer to make a conqueſt of that, which God will haue obtained by iuſt and peaceable meanes.</p>
            <p>And though you were lawfully annoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and Crowned King of <hi>Fraunce</hi> (Sir) tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly we would graunt to the <hi>Huguenots</hi> that which they ſay, that in oppoſing our ſelues a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gainſt your will and ordinaunces, (were it for the miſtruſt of our Religion) we would be diſobedient and rebellious, for ſince that we haue alwaies accuſed them, to haue cari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Armes againſt their Prince, and laying vpon vs the like reproche, they doo condemne them ſelues in that behalfe: it is good reaſon that we ſuffer the ſelfe ſame lawe, which we our ſelues haue made againſt others. But there is too great a difference, betwéen to be a King, and to carry pretence to the royalty: for the firſt, true it is, that we are forbidden to reſiſt the King, but not him that would make himſelfe King againſt the Lawes of the Realme, and it is to be noted, that for to ſuccéed in a royaltie, the lawe is much more to be conſidered then nature, pardon me (ſir) if I ſpeak ſomewhat liberally, for I ſhould
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:21035:9"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> betray you, in vſing diſguiſings &amp; diſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, in affaires y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> are of ſuch co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſeque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce.</p>
            <p>If we ſhould haue regarde but to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> néere alliance in blood, thoſe which within theſe fiftie yéeres are iſſued of the Daughters of <hi>Fraunce,</hi> ſhould be much more néer then you, and if you anſwere that the Lawe dooth ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude the daughters from the ſucceſſion of the Realme: you are to conſider, that the ſelfe ſame law dooth likewiſe exclude thoſe which are ſeperated from the Church. And albeit that ſuch excluſions are not there expreſſed, the beléefe which at all times we haue repo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in God, and the vſage and fourme of his ſeruice: are vniuerſall Lawes which God hath planted in the hartes of men, againſt the which there néedeth not the Caueat of any particuler lawe, for they haue force and authoritie ſufficient for their part, which the <hi>Salicque</hi> lawe cannot haue.</p>
            <p>What Sir? If God had permitted that the Prince which ſhould next ſuccéed in this Crown, were a <hi>Iew</hi> or a <hi>Mahometan:</hi> would you think that it were reaſonable to admit him? Now if we were driuen to ſhowe, that neither the <hi>Turk</hi> nor the <hi>Iewe</hi> are more odi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and contrary to our Religion, then the <hi>Huguenot</hi> is, I would bring foorth no other proofe, but the proper diſcourſe of your Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters:
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:21035:10"/>
at leaſt we might auouch that there could be no greater wunder, then to ſée a <hi>Huguenot</hi> weare the Crowne of <hi>Fraunce.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Truely Sir, thoſe doo very much deceiue you, who goe about to put in your head; that you ſhal finde forces ſufficient, to ſuch an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſt partaking, for I wiſh you to conſider, that there are in <hi>Fraunce</hi> other princes of the blood, beſide you: of the which the moſte née<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt to the Crowne, which ſhould be found to be a Catholique, by the conſent and appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation of all the Eſtates, and of the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of this Realme, ſhould in this caſe be eſtéemed and taken for a lawfull ſucceſſour, and yet none ſhould be able to ſay, that any thing were chaunged in the lawful and aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient ſucceſſion: becauſe neither you nor any other might be eſtéemed to be in the order of ſucceſſion, ſo long as they ſhould iudge you vncapable for that calling.</p>
            <p>What could you doo then with thoſe ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gined forces propounded vnto you, but to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt in vaine, againſt the right, iuſtice and al the obſeruations of this Monarchie? ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore henceforward (Sir) you are to knowe, that reaſon is a mighty and puiſſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t enemy, I confeſſe and graunt to thoſe pretended re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligeous men, that the <hi>Switzers</hi> and the <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netians</hi> are auncient fréends, and allyed with
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:21035:10"/>
the Kings of <hi>Fraunce:</hi> but whome (to their Iudgements) would theſe Nations holde for a King, then the firſt Prince of the blood, capable, annoynted &amp; conſecrated, according to the ordinary cuſtoms, and to whome all the Eſtates haue ſworne their fidelitie, and the commons their true obedience. Theſe Nations are (ſauing fews) auncient Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liques, and your perſwaders will make you beléeue, that they will take Armes to put the Scepter of <hi>Fraunce,</hi> into the handes of a <hi>Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guenot,</hi> againſt the lawes of the Countrye, and Chriſtendome: but contrarywiſe make your account, that all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Nations allyed with this Crown, would be againſt you, as to him that fighteth in an euill cauſe, and an vniuſt title.</p>
            <p>But to bring this to paſſe, <hi>Fraunce</hi> ſhould haue no néed to make any leuey of forraine forces, neither ſhould <hi>Spaine</hi> nor <hi>Italy</hi> he ſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licited to come to our aide: what need we the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> but keep our ſelues in our own eſtate? what mean haue you the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wherby to enforce vs? la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing al vanity &amp; flattery aſide, let vs acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge our ſelues what we are. What hope can you haue to bring to your bowe, ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny great townes, ſo many ſtrong holdes, and a people ſo warlike as the <hi>Frenchmen</hi> are? Doo you not think, that though you had all
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:21035:11"/>
               <hi>England,</hi> and <hi>Germany</hi> with you, and we ſhould ſtand but vpon your owne defence: yet ſhould not you be able in ten ſuch ages as yours is, to get the maiſterſhip of <hi>Guyen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne</hi> only, for what other men can you hope dooth fauour you, but only the <hi>Germains</hi> and the <hi>Engliſhmen?</hi> As for the <hi>Flemings</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides that they are but of little account, yet they haue woorke enough to doo at home.</p>
            <p>Dooth it pleaſe you to conſider a little, what helpe you may expect of <hi>England?</hi> It is a Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in an Iland, and which cannot come to you but by Sea: where will you land all this Armie? All the Hauens in <hi>Fraunce</hi> be againſt you. If you truſt <hi>Rochell:</hi> you haue ſéen with your eyes héertofore, that by the meanes of a defence made with Pales vpon the mouth of the Chanell, and placing certaine veſſells of Warre before, we haue driuen back fiue and fifty <hi>Engliſh</hi> Sayle which came in ſight, and yet durſt approche no néerer then the Cannon ſhot. We haue yet the ſelfe meanes that we had then, and you haue none at all wherby to let vs: now, to hazard a battell of <hi>Frenchmen</hi> to <hi>Frenchmen,</hi> to open them the frée paſſage, I am aſſured that no man will giue you ſuch councel. You haue ſéen hether<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we néed but foure companies of men of Armes, with the Catholique Footmen of the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:21035:11"/>
ſame cuntry where your greateſt forces lye, to kéep you encloſed within your own Gari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons. And although you might ioyne with the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Army, how great doo you think it would be? the Realm is little, and perad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenture not to frée from partialitie and diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion: ſo that they cannot forgoe any great number of their men, without giuing a fitte occaſion to the contrary parte, to riſe &amp; take their owne aduauntage.</p>
            <p>You knowe how great the ſuccour hath béen, which they haue ſent to the <hi>Flemings</hi> their neighbours, though it was to fauour ſo great a Prince, as <hi>Monſieur</hi> the only brother to the King, who had as it ſéemeth a greater and more particuler intelligence in that Cuntry, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you can haue in this. Therfore, you ought not look for any greater aide from that Cuntrie, then he: and with ſo ſmalle a number, there is no great likelyhood that you ſhould much preuaile in your affaires. For if they could conuay into this Realme ſo great forces, that they were ſufficient to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſh you in the Royaltie, the taking of <hi>New Hauen</hi> hath giuen vs to vnderſtand, and it is to be preſumed, that they which doo vpholde the Crown of <hi>Fraunce,</hi> both in their hartes and titles: would not vſe ſuch Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie towards you, as to trauaile rather for you
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:21035:12"/>
then for their owne proper ſelues. I wil not héere diſcourſe what woork we might giue them at home, wherby we might withdraw them ſoone out of <hi>Fraunce,</hi> and ſo driue them to regarde their own Cuntry: for you know very well the greatnes and power of that Cuntry.</p>
            <p>And as touching the <hi>Germaynes,</hi> call to your remembrance Sir, that when the <hi>Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guenots</hi> were in their beſt ſtrength, and (as on might ſay) in the very flower of their age, and that all things ſéemed to ſmile on them, and that many yéers before (by the crop they made in <hi>Fraunce</hi>) they had laid vp great tre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, they called to their ſuccour ſo many <hi>Ruitters</hi> as they could: and yet for al this they cannot make any reckoning of any on victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry on their ſide. So that if the <hi>Ruitters</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member themſelues: they ought to be more affraid to approche néere the <hi>Frenchmen,</hi> then the <hi>Frenchmen</hi> ſhould de diſcouraged to ſée them in their Country.</p>
            <p>But now at this time, wherin the <hi>Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guenots</hi> are vpon theire deelining: and (as it were) vpon their graues (as commonly we ſée that féeble things are of no long continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance) and that their ſhoulders doo bowe with the blowes we haue giuen them, yea, that they haue not one teaſter, becauſe they can
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:21035:12"/>
finde nothing more to gleane in this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome: wherupon then can they ground this their imagination, to cauſe the <hi>Germaynes</hi> to ruſh foorth into <hi>Fraunce,</hi> to ſtrengthe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you? If we ſhould make any account of the affecti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on which they doo beare to the cauſe: doo you think (Sir) they wil be more pricked with deuotion to make you King, then they were before to eſtabliſh the <hi>Huguenot</hi> Religion?</p>
            <p>As touching the generall grounding of ones Religion, it ſéemeth that all men are prouoked therto by a naturall affection: but what occaſion haue they ſo to loue your per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, as in making you King, they would for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goe their owne commodity and quietnes? what manner of importance is it to them, who were King of <hi>Fraunce?</hi> If therfore you haue made triall, that to cauſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> mount on horſeback, you muſt haue your purſſe to be heard Iyngle, &amp; not ſpeak deafly, &amp; that ſince the declining of the <hi>Huguenots</hi> forces, they would not ſtirre, being neuer ſo often called by them: by what reaſon doo you hope that they would come to you <hi>gratis,</hi> to rule an E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate wherin they haue nothing to doo? Put the caſe that theſe things were ſo deſperate, as they muſt be called, vnder the condition to vſe <hi>Fraunce,</hi> as a Cuntry allready gotten: ſhould this be any other thing then héerto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:21035:13"/>
hath béen offered them? &amp; when y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> likely<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>hoods did promiſe ſome ſucceſſe to the enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſe? and beſides this they knowe, that the accompliſhment of this condition dependeth not on the conuention made, but on the victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. And if you take them for ſuch as in déed they are, that is hirelings, and ſeruing them that offer moſte: what greater aſſurance can you giue them now for their pay, when you ſhall finde your ſelfe in like termes of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute for the Crowne of <hi>Fraunce,</hi> as in times paſt? Where are your new treaſurs? where are your demeanes in <hi>Fraunce?</hi> would you not then ſeaze vpon them? what if they would no more to your commaundement then, than they doo now?</p>
            <p>As for that you might recouer by way of borowing in <hi>England,</hi> you would be but lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle the richer therby, For when you haue gotten fiftie thouſand Crownes vpon Iew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> value of two hundreth thouſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d as the Quéene your mother did, that would be the vttermoſte in all the world: yet this ſuffizeth not to make thrée muſters, of the two leaſte Garriſons which you haue. I leaue aſide the ſmall commoditie you ſhould finde, to ſend forces to méet the <hi>Ruitters,</hi> to back them when they enter the Realme, if in caſe you had made leuey of them.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:21035:13"/>But admit that all things ſhould fall out according as you doo hope for: doo you not think that he which ſhallbe conſecrated and proclaimed king of <hi>Fraunce,</hi> who ſhould haue in his hand all the Townes and forces of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Realme, who ſhall diſpoſe of the treaſure and riches of the ſame at his owne pleaſure, and who ſhall maintaine the ancient allian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of this Crowne: doo you not think I ſay that for a hundred of your <hi>Ruitters,</hi> he will cauſe that ten thouſand ſhall come?</p>
            <p>Then ſince you knowe Sir that this na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is accuſtomed to let out to him their har<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dines and blood: why doo not you perſwade your ſelfe, that he which giueth moſte, ſhall haue moſte of them? Haue we not ſéene that the King hath had more of them, and more often then y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
               <hi>Huguenots</hi> haue, and ſuch haue taken the Kings parte againſt them, who firſt were with them againſt the King?</p>
            <p>Furthermore, are we not able to breake your determinations with the <hi>Germains,</hi> in giuing them more money to tarry at home, then you can giue them to come hether, to haue their heads broken? Are not we able to ſowe &amp; maintain ſuch diuiſions amongſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (which are already partly brought to effect) which will bridle them ſo ſhort, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> them ſo néerly at home, that they ſhall haue
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:21035:14"/>
no leiſure to think vpon their neighbours affaires? Beholde héer Sir, the great effects which by all diſcourſe of reaſon, you may expect aſwell of <hi>England</hi> as off <hi>Germanye.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>They tell you (to put you in comfort) that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
               <hi>Huguenots</hi> make the third part of <hi>Fraunce.</hi> If you haue regiſtred in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> book of your houſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde, ſuch Calculators for your inſtructions in Arithmatique, that betime you wil croſſe them out againe: otherwiſe I forſée that you are in da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger to become a very bad Arithma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticion. But to the end you ſhould not rely on ſuch rediculous and fantaſticall preſumpti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, what doo it auaile to you how great ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer the number of <hi>Huguenots</hi> are in this Realme, ſéeing when it coms to handiblows they are not on your ſide, neither wil ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then your cauſe. And where vpon can you ground this opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that if you were in that poynt, euen to ſtriue for the Kingdome: that they will ſhowe them ſelues rather to be on your ſide, then they haue doon héertofore whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you ſtroue for Religion? can one poſſibly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>léeue, that they will be more hardly to make you King, then they haue béen to authoriſe their own beléefe? ſurely it ſhould not ſéeme true.</p>
            <p>Now I come to the inconuenience wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto you may runne, (as they alleadge) if
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:21035:14"/>
you forſake the <hi>Huguenots</hi> parte. In caſe (ſay they) you ſhould fall into any diſagréement with the King, you ſhould behold the ſupport which hitherto hath maintained you againſt him: or if any ſtranger ſhould meddle with you, you ſhould hardly finde any where els, ſuch a faithful &amp; an aſſured force, as you haue tried in them of the refourmed Religion. What Sir? will they inferre, that whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer you doo, you may at leaſt be alwaies aſſu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red, to be able to wadge warre with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> King when you pleaſe? Dare they well confeſſe, that the Subiect hath no meane to rebell a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his Prince, except the <hi>Huguenots</hi> be the inſtrument for the ſame? I leaue this talke, becauſe it is too proper for an Inuec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue. But this I will ſay Sir, that in reſpect of the quarrells which you might haue ſtra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, you néed not doubt to become a Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique, for feare leaſt your force would be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſhed thereby: the power of the King (which is not much leſſe then that of the <hi>Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guenots</hi>) would be imployed for your defence, for if you doo not refuſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to ſtra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gers who haue put them ſelues vnder his protecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, what likelyhood is there that he wil deny them to you, béeing a Prince of his blood, his Subiect, and his Brother in lawe?</p>
            <p>For the reſolution of this diſcourſe Sir,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:21035:15"/>
I doo ſay vnto you, that you becomming a ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholique, you make your poſſeſt of the Kings fauour, conuert to you the affection of the Nobilitie, aſſure your ſelfe of the good will and force of the eſtate, doo eſtabliſh your au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie, and winne again the harts of al the people: Contrarywiſe, remaining and <hi>Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guenot,</hi> you doo eſtrange your ſelfe from the King, with the moſte odious ſeperatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of all, doo cauſe that the whole eſtate doo not only miſtruſt you, but alſo abhorre you, &amp; which is not to be a little conſidered, you prepare your ſelfe a continuall gréef for the remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of your life, &amp; after your death a perpetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all ſpot to your houſe, that by imbracing an opinion, and a new conceit of a Preacher, you depriue your ſelfe of ſuch a rich and an honourable inheritaunce, as the Crowne of <hi>Fraunce.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>How can you think that the poſteritie will let paſſe in ſilence, the reproches which they are to obiect againſt you, when it ſhall be tolde them, that <hi>Henry</hi> the Second, King of <hi>Nauarre,</hi> did rather imbrace the hope of ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bilitie, to Kindle fire in this Realme, and make it ruinate by warre, then the councell wherby he might eaſly be a peacable ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſour therof: &amp; though your perſwaders haue like hope, yet is their want of good councell,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:21035:15"/>
and let your Maieſtie pardone me for vſing theſe ſpéeches. For it is not credible, that con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tinuing ſtil in this pretended Religion: you can therby make greater ſture for y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Crown or aſſemble greater forces then thoſe which you haue at this time: but rather in ſo dooing you ſhall make them the leſſer.</p>
            <p>Now I leaue it to your Iudgement, if in this preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t eſtate of your affaires, it were expedient for you to enterpriſe warre a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Catholiques: or if their were any occaſion wherby you might eſtéeme, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> your enterpriſe ſhould proſper y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> better. As for me if I were on your ſide, as God forbid, I ſée what better cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cel on might giue you the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (for al your Armour) to haue a recourſe to the ver<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tue of patience and to comfort your ſelf with the faire diſcourſe of the contempt of the world, and ſhortnes of this life, a noble and Philoſophicall reſolution in déed: wherein<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o your Miniſters labour to bring you. Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ertheleſſe I graunt them that to forſake God and chaunge religion, for great riches <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd high calling, is a moſte abiect and dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>able thing: but to whome may we better <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ue this reproche, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to ſuch as are depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d from the Catholique Church, the Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> of their forefathers, and the faith wherin <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ey receiued their Baptiſme.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:21035:16"/>Let al thoſe of the pretended Religion ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>amine their conſciences, and vtter in good ſooth, by what meanes eche of them hath béen induced to renounce the ancient beléefe, and receiue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> new: if there be any one whom God (by particuler communication) hath in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpired ſo to doo, he hath very great reaſon to kéep him ſelfe firme and vnchangeable. But if the ignorant people perceiue, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they haue béen induced therunto only by the entiſings of a ſwéet and eloquent language and by the inclinations which naturally all men haue to new inuentions, which I ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not tell what baite of libertie of their conſciences, by the means of a few learned me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, who forſaking y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> great number and multitude of others, haue gotten in amongſt you, to get a particuler fame to themſelues, while they beheld that the proſperous winde and fauour of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple did aptly ſerue their turne, and that the Princes, and great Lords were drawen heer to by other worldly conſiderations, and not for Religion: wherfore the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (in knowing that this is through our weakneſſe that we haue taken on that part) doo we not come againe to him who hath béen our nouriſher, by the inſtitution of our Aunceſters, and to whom God hath euidently declared, that all things ſhould be to vs happy and proſperous? what
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:21035:16"/>
ſée we in this Religion héer, which we haue not behelde in all other new ſects and opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons? haue not the <hi>Albigeois</hi> in their time dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen ſo many of the people to their opinion, that they could make a whole Army of them? And it is not ſo eaſily put in proofe, as with a ſimple people, if one haue but only y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> meane, to tickle them in the eares with ſwéet and pleaſing woords. Doo you not doubt, but if the ſelfe ſame entrance were permitted to a <hi>Mahometane,</hi> as hath béen giuen to a <hi>Hugue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not:</hi> it ſhould not be long before he would put his <hi>Alcharon</hi> in credit, and to cary ſway thorowe all <hi>Fraunce.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You Sir, to whome the conſequence of this matter is of greater moment the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to any other: ought to examine your owne ſelfe, and to knowe what occaſions haue induced you to it, and whan dooth kéep you therin. Hath God héerin extraordinarily inſpired you, or els the déep knowledge which you haue in Diuinitie? hath it brought you to this newe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ight of veritie? If you acknowledge that it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s neither of them, how is it poſſible that you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hould conſent to departe from the vniuerſal <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> léefe: to followe the fantaſies and inuenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ns of a Man borne in our age? Are you ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aſily perſwaded to ſuch opinions as they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>leaſe? will you ſuffer your ſelfe to be bewit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:21035:17"/>
with woords? Doo you think you ſhal not be iudged very weake, and of ſlender re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution in all your other actions? If you wil be miſſ-led on this faſhion, in matters which concerne your ſaluation and Religion: what ſhalbe ſaid but thus? That a Prince of high and noble vnderſtanding, leaft the lawe and faith of his Aunceſters, to take an opinion at the firſt ſight, without hauing in him ſelfe any other ground of reaſon, wherfore he ſhould doo ſo.</p>
            <p>Thoſe that doo followe the Religion and fourmes of their predeceſſours, haue euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more reaſon ſo to doo. For we wil hold it for certaine, that God béeing come for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption of the world, did ordaine by his owne mouth to ſuch men as then were, thoſe things which he would that they ſhould be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>léeue and obſerue: and we doo trye euery day that it is naturall for vs, to teache and deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer to our ſucceſſours, the ſame things which we haue receiued of our Aunceſtors. But to reproue and condemne the ancient traditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s by the impreſſion and opinion of others, and not to haue in our owne ſelues ſome inward knowledge, wherfore they ought ſo to doo: this ſéemeth to me of all other vnexcuſable, in the continuance of ſo many ages, by vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſall obſeruation.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:21035:17"/>Haue we nothing wherwithal to confirm our beléefe, againſt a new ſence or meaning, which ſome Scholler (deſirous to ſhowe his ſkil) wil apply to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy ſcripture? hath it béen errour which men haue beléeued hithertoo? and when God hath ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t vs moſte of his bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gs, hath it béen a ſigne that our ſeruice hath béen leſſe acceptable to him? Or els are we ſo blinde that we will not acknowledge, how God gaue vs all things more proſperouſly, when (without any trouble) the Catholique faith was moſte religiouſly obſerued?</p>
            <p>The Kings your predeceſſors Sir, who haue left ſo many faire foundations, ſo many and holy ordinances, and illuſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Conqueſts: haue they euer béen any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then Catholiques? If the Kingdomes haue had any ſplendour and increaſe: hath it béen at any other time, but when the people continued ſtedfaſt in the beléefe, which they would now cauſe you to reiect? And if they haue had any decay or ruine: hath it béen at any other time then when nouelties haue caryed authoritie?</p>
            <p>Eache one knowes, that <hi>Clouis</hi> the firſt Chriſtian King of <hi>Fraunce,</hi> reigned fiue hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred yéers or there about after the death of our Sauiour, at which time the primitiue Church did yet flooriſh. If the Church then
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:21035:18"/>
had ſome holy and ſincere obſeruations: doo you think ſhe did hide or ſpare them, at the conſecration of that King of <hi>Fraunce,</hi> who of a <hi>Pagan</hi> became a Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? Oh what a like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly thing is it to beléeue, that the fourmes at this preſent day obſerued, at the Coronati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of our Kings, are not the ſelfe ſame that were inſtituted for the Crowning of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaide <hi>Clouis?</hi> If I ſhould admit, that in the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Cerimonies, and which are indifferent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vſed of eche one, there might ſome abuſe créep in, what then? As for the Cerimonies vſed at the conſecration of our Kings, an act wherto all the world at all times haue born like reuerence, and an act both ſinguler and religious, wherof (ſince <hi>Clouis</hi>) but thréeſcore perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s haue béen partakers, ſucceſſiuely one after an other: who wil beléeue that in them there hath béen any alteration or chaunge? And if it be ſo, that the Cerimonies vſed at the Coronation of the Kinges of <hi>Fraunce,</hi> be the inſtitutions of the primitiue Churche: how can one giue eare to the Miniſters of the pretended Religion ſéeing thoſe thinges which they iudge woorſt in the Catholique Church, are therin intirely obſerued.</p>
            <p>Let vs knowe a little by what prooues they can ſhowe vs, that the inſtitutions and Eccleſiaſticall orders, which at this day are
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:21035:18"/>
vſed amongſt the Catholiques, be other then they were in the primitiue Church: it muſt followe neceſſarily (as I beleeue) that they ſhalbe the books and writings of the Biſhops of the ſame Church. But without entring into diſpute of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> depth of this matter, where it is moſte certaine y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they are abuſed: what will they anſwere if they were demaunded, how they knowe that ſuch Books and wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings are auncient and not ſuppoſed? What other anſwere could they make, but that ſince the time they were made, the Church hath euermore held them for the true wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings of the Authors, of whome they beare the name, and that from hand to hand ſhe hath conuaied them vnto vs, for ſuch If then to proue the trueth of a writing, they think that the vniuerſall and continuall allowa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce for many yéers, is an argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t which no one ought to gainſay: why doo they not holde the ſelf ſame allowance and vniuerſall approba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, for a moſte certaine proofe of the verity, of the ancient obſeruations and inſtitutions of the Church?</p>
            <p>Where haue we found that men wil ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit leſſe abuſe and corruption to enter, then into their beleef, and the lawes wheron they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>udge) dependeth their ſaluation? hath the
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:21035:19"/>
               <hi>Huguenot</hi> found the Catholique Church, ſo ready to receiue thoſe nouelties, which he we<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t about to bring in? doo they think that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though a <hi>Pope</hi> would cauſe vs (as it were to morowe) to chaunge our beléefe, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we would therfore beléeue him? and thoſe things which we our ſelues will not doo, is it to be preſupo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed that our predeceſſours haue doone them? they were more religious, and better obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers of godlines, then we are. Doo they not ſée, that in the fourmes which only concerne the pollicye and gouernment amongſt men, and the Lawes made for their contracts and particuler affaires: y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſucceſſours doo not light<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly change y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> which hath béen eſtabliſhed (at the firſt foundation of the eſtate) by their pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>deceſſours, as it is eaſy to be noted in all pol<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>litique eſtates, but chéefly our <hi>Fraunce,</hi> which at this preſent day, is the moſte auncient Monarchie of all? If then it be apparant that the people haue alwaies béen conſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, in ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruing the ciuill and humaine lawes: what ought they to haue doon in the conſeruation of thoſe, which haue béen giuen the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for their dutie to God, and to the Church?</p>
            <p>Is it not known how long time y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
               <hi>Iewes</hi> haue kept without any change, the fourmes and cerimonies of the olde lawe? Why ſhall we not ſay that the Chriſtians haue doon the
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:21035:19"/>
like? The <hi>Huguenots</hi> Doo think, that they haue giuen a faire ſhowe and precious title to their Religeon, when they ſay they will admit nothing els, but the ſimple and pure woord of God, as it is contained in the books of the olde and new Teſtament, and from thence driue out and exclude all humaine traditions. Permit me Sir, to demaunde of them héere, if their ſcope be not to maintain all kinde of men, in the knowledge and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>léefe of God: and if in conſcience they think that this may be alwaies doone, by the only hearing of the woord?</p>
            <p>As for thoſe that haue béen ſo happy, as to heare the liuely voice of God, or of his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples: I wil graunt that they néeded no other inſtruction. But as humaine kinde hath béen farre diſtant from that liuely and ſpeaking light, which did rauiſh the people with their brightnes and piercing ſpeach: ſo vndoubted<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly there hath béen a great decay in zeale and beléef: for there is great reaſon betwéen the woords pronounced by the mouth of God, and thoſe vttered by the mouth of a man.</p>
            <p>Not long after, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this woord was but written, ſome were found, who would en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpret the ſame according to their ſence and meaning, which was an euident teſtimony, that the only preaching of theſe men, was
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:21035:20"/>
not a band ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g enough, wherby to reſtrain the braines of men in godlines: the Churche therfore perceiuing this want, brought in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> remedy, framing her ſelfe to the weakneſſe of men, ſet foorth (in time which ſhe thought néedfull) by viſible and ordinary things, that which the Chriſtians ought to obſerue and beléeue, as in a painted table, to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> end, that the ſight and exerciſe therof, might fortefie and repreſent to them at eache time, that which might eaſely ſlide from their ſoule, béeing receiued but by hearing only.</p>
            <p>From thence ſprang the originall, of the fourmes &amp; Cerimonies of our Catholique Religion. It may be, that in one time or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther there haue béen more or leſſe. For as at the firſt eſtabliſhing and foundation of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealths, men made but few lawes, and afterwarde the mallice and fraud of men in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſing: it was neceſſary that many other lawes ſhould be made, as obſtacles and lets to many vices &amp; peruerſe qualities of men. Likewiſe the Church in her firſt age, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in impietie had leſſe power, had no néed at her beginning of ſo many ordinances. But as new yéers brought vs new vices: by her inſtitutions ſhe met with the prograce of our frailtie, to ſtop his paſſage. Yet for all this, ſhe hath béene one ſelf ſame Churche,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:21035:20"/>
though the occaſions to ordaine more or leſſe ordinances, haue been diuers.</p>
            <p>The lawes and ſtatutes which ſhe was driuen to commaund, to let our negligence or careleſſenes of holy things, or our vnbeléefe: are thoſe which the <hi>Huguenots</hi> will fight a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>againſt. Dooth it not ſéeme (Sir) that they haue reaſon? They ſay, that there are abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, that may be: but what? is it likely that the Lawe ſhould be reiected, becauſe (perad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenture) it hath ſome ruſt ouer it?</p>
            <p>Will it pleaſe you (Sir) a little to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, the birth and forwardnes of this preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded Religion? mark wel theſe things, which they that haue brought in this, demaund to be cut off from our Religion: and you ſhall finde y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they would annihilate thoſe fourms, wherby the people are holden in the feare of God, or the deminiſhing of the credence we haue in his omnipotency, or els they would induce vs to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> diſobeying of our ſuperiours, or condemne the orders and pollicye of the Church, or make vs leſſe deuout, and leſſe charitable one to an other, or els they would pluck out of our harts the affection and me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morye of our Aunceſters, and the honor and reuerence of thoſe, whome we iudge that God ought to haue better accepted their liues. And afterward regarde, what they
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:21035:21"/>
will haue thoſe men to ſtudy, whome they would ſend into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world to preach their doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine: you ſée that it is nothing appertai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to diuinitie, but a pleaſing language, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected, entiſing, and inuecting, becauſe that ſcience is contrary to their artificiall deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations, but elloquence is proper to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawe and ſeduce. Conſider alſo what Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions haue imbraced this, and you ſhal finde that they are ſuch, who are noted of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to be prompt, inconſiderate, and loouers of new fa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gled things, as are the <hi>Germaines, Flemings</hi> and <hi>Engliſhmen,</hi> and we alſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> are of the North parte. And in the natio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s more ſtayed and iudiciall, as are the <hi>Italians</hi> &amp; <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nyards,</hi> it could neuer finde an entraunce there: where it behooueth now a little to iudge without affection, of the manners of the moſte parte of them haue receiued it, and doo followe it. Conſider withall the ſuddaine decreaſe, or rather annihillating of this Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion: ſcarſely is ſhe born, but ſhe is deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ed in the beginni<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g: ſhe makes a faire ſhowe of her forces, and al at once behold ſhe is fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len, and brought downe to the ground: and to ſhowe vs her pride in the fall wherin ſhe is, ſhe boaſteth that ſhe is victorious: al that remaines with her, and ſhe hath not loſt, ſhe counteth for a gaine and victory.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:21035:21"/>What ſay they? there are but few yéeres that we were kept priſoners and perſecuted, but now notwithſtanding all the battailes you haue gotten againſt vs, it is neuerthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe frée for vs to praiſe publiquely our God, and to reprehend aloud and openly in your eares, the abuſes of your Church: is not this to haue vanquiſhed? But what els is the ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument of the <hi>Iewes,</hi> when they doo vpholde, that the Prophecies of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> comming of Chriſt is not as yet accompliſhed, and y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the Scepter is not as yet taken away from the Tribe of <hi>Iuda?</hi> They doo not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider, that now a daies it is no more their Religion that ſtandeth, but their factions in her leagues: ſo we were driuen to agrée with them, as with people that defend their parte with Armes.</p>
            <p>Their Religion is condemned for ſuch as neuer was: but the deſire to pacifie the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate, and take away the miſeries which di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſions dooth bring, is the cauſe that thoſe doo liue in libertie, whom we leaue not to holde as guiltie. If with only patience they had o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uercome thoſe afflictions laide vpon them, there were found ſome likelyhood of y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> which they ſay, that their faith hath béen victorious: but ſince it is by Armes, that little libertie which they haue, is due not to their godlynes but to their ſwoords, becauſe in an eſtate deui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:21035:22"/>
in two factions, it is hard that one ſhould ſo ſoone get the victorie ouer the other. This muſt goe by degree and foot by foot: and then they may perceiue what decay their owne hath had hetherto.</p>
            <p>Since then (Sir) that they haue tried, how our Kings neither can nor wil forbeare and maintaine them, neither giue them the libertie which they could wiſh in this Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholique Realme, becauſe (in ſo dooing) he ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not be King of <hi>Fraunce:</hi> it ſéemeth vnto me (Sir) that they auaile nothing for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues, and doo you but very ill ſeruice, to diſſwade you from reuniting to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Catholique church, conſidering that if it ſhould ſo happen, that God would call you to this Crowne, they ought with better reaſon expect more gentle vſage at your handes, then of any other. As touching vs, the examples which we ſée in thoſe places, where the <hi>Hugenotes</hi> haue the ſoueraigne authoritie and force: what can we els expect at their hands, but our whole ruine, if we haue a King, who will ſuffer him ſelfe to be perſwaded by the Miniſters.</p>
            <p>I will conclude with this woord Sir, that it is peraduenture tollerable to al other per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, when the féebleneſſe of their ſoules cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth them to goe aſtray from their dutie to God, by the meanes of men: but this can in
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:21035:22"/>
no wiſe be to you, who haue this particuler fauour, to be iſſued of the blood of the moſte Chriſtian Kings, who holde ſuch a great and high place in Chriſtendo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e, by the highneſſe they haue gotten you, being Catholiques: you are at leaſt for this bound to their me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory, not to reiect the Religion which they haue euer followed. Set before your eyes the deceaſſed King your Father, and call in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to remembrance, that he alwaies hath béene y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> moſte aſſured ſtay, &amp; faithful protectour of this crown: doo you think then y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it ſhalbe ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>norable for you, to maintaine and fight on that partye, againſt whom ſo willingly hée imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him ſelfe, and loſt his life?</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
